<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of the Parliament and their proceedings. Or, Their military designe prov'd loyall and legall. A treatise, wherein these things are ingeniously and sincerely handled; to wit, 1. That the militia as setled by the Parliament is lawfull. 2. That it is lawfull for us to obey it, so setled by them. 3. That the Parliament is not by us to be deserted. 4. That in aiding the Parliament the king is not opposed. 5. That the Parliament (as the case stands) may not confide in the king. 6. That this necessary defensive warre of theirs is indubitably justifiable. Pulchrum pro Patria mori,</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W808aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E122_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19259</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112749</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112749)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E122[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of the Parliament and their proceedings. Or, Their military designe prov'd loyall and legall. A treatise, wherein these things are ingeniously and sincerely handled; to wit, 1. That the militia as setled by the Parliament is lawfull. 2. That it is lawfull for us to obey it, so setled by them. 3. That the Parliament is not by us to be deserted. 4. That in aiding the Parliament the king is not opposed. 5. That the Parliament (as the case stands) may not confide in the king. 6. That this necessary defensive warre of theirs is indubitably justifiable. Pulchrum pro Patria mori,</title>
                  <author>Ward, Richard, 1601 or 2-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare. MDCXLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Richard Ward.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politcs and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112749:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION OF THE PARLIAMENT And their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>OR, Their Military Deſigne prov'd Loyall and Legall.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> wherein theſe things are ingeniouſly and ſincerely handled; to wit,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the</hi> MILITIA as ſetled by the PARLIAMENT <hi>is lawfull.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That it is lawfull for us to obey it, ſo ſetled by</hi> Them.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That the</hi> PARLIAMENT <hi>is not by us to be deſerted.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That in aiding the</hi> PARLIAMENT <hi>the</hi> KING <hi>is not oppoſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>That the</hi> PARLIAMENT <hi>(as the caſe ſtands) may not confide in the King.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>That this neceſſary Defenſive</hi> WARRE <hi>of</hi> Theirs <hi>is indubitably juſtifiable.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pulchrum pro Patria mori,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeare. MDCXLII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:112749:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112749:2"/>
            <head>The Vindication of the PARLIAMENT and their PROCEEDINGS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He maine thing now looked upon,<note place="margin">What is now prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally enquired after.</note> and pried into by all eyes, is the nature of this preſent <hi>Martiall</hi> and <hi>Military Deſigne</hi> undertaken by the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Now although much hath beene writien by many upon this <hi>Subject,</hi> yet divers well diſpoſed and well affected perſons, are very unſetled and unreſolved, what to thinke thereof; and the Reaſons hereof I conceive to bee theſe; to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">5. Reaſons why the vulgar ſort are unſatisfied in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> That compendious kind of writing which ſome uſe in laying downe onely the particular <hi>Head,</hi> by way of aſſertion, without either amplification, application or proofe; whence he who is not informed or thorowly inſighted into the truth, and nature of that which is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is ready to conclude it a fallacie, <hi>Petitio quaeſiti, &amp; dare</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it upon the <hi>Authors</hi> bare word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That abſtruſe, ſublime and high ſtile which others uſe in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, thinking all apprehenſions as <hi>quick,</hi> and judgements as <hi>profound,</hi> and <hi>underſtandings</hi> as <hi>cleare</hi> as ther owne; and thus not ſtooping to the capacity of vulgar <hi>Readers,</hi> leave them as perplexed and as much unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied as they found them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That confuſed kind of writing which ſome have; for as <hi>Method</hi> doth much helpe both the <hi>memory</hi> and <hi>vnderſtanding;</hi> ſo <hi>immethodicall diſcourſes</hi> doe confound both <hi>underſtanding</hi> and <hi>judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſleight and ſuperficiall kind of writing which others have, who never ſearching themſelves into the depth, life and bottome of the point in hand, leave their <hi>Reader</hi> juſt ſo wiſe as they found him.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112749:3"/>
            <p n="5">5. That timerous and halfe handling of the caſe in controverſie, which ſome are guilty of; for ſome have taken the point in hand, but fearing <hi>Veritas odium parit,</hi> that <hi>Truth will come home with a ſcratcht face,</hi> dare not ſay what they can, may ſhould or ought of the point, for the full ſatisfaction of their <hi>Reader;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving him by this means altogether without light in the moſt materiall things which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to inſtruct him in.</p>
            <p>And therefore becauſe I will never refuſe to ſacrifice my life, much leſſe ſpare any paines for the welfare, ſafety and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>vation of my <hi>Countrey,</hi> the preventing of theſe <hi>Civill wars</hi> threat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> compoſing of our preſent diſtractions, and the ſatisfaction of tender conſciences, to the utmoſt of my ability, I have with what brevity, ſincerity, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and clearneſſe poſſibly I could, declared unto all, who deſire to be ſatisfied what they may conceive and imagine of the true nature of the <hi>preſent Deſigne</hi> of the State and condition wherein we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and what ſeemes to be intended and aimed at by both <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not trouble my ſelfe to ſearch <hi>Record,</hi> nor preſume to expound, and interpret <hi>Lawes,</hi> (being no Lawyer) but only ſlow the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of this <hi>Deſigne,</hi> as farre as the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>humune Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>experience,</hi> and my ſmall <hi>knowledge</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> will dictate unto me.</p>
            <p>Againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> two things are excepted;<note place="margin">Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons taken againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> their <hi>Act,</hi> and the <hi>Effect</hi> of that <hi>Act:</hi> or, their <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Intention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Action</hi> is the putting of the Kingdome into a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, by ſettling of the <hi>Militia</hi> without the aſſent of the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Intention</hi> herein is ſuppoſed or ſurmiſed to be the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of themſelves againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and the raiſing of Forces againſt his power. Now, of both theſe ſeverally.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Militia</hi> two <hi>quaere's</hi> are ordinarily made;<note place="margin">The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Militia lawfull.</note> to wit,
<list>
                  <item>1. Whether it be lawfull for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to ſettle it without the <hi>Royall</hi> aſſent.</item>
                  <item>2. Whether it be lawfull for us to obey it, ſo ſetled by <hi>Them?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> Firſt, it may be demanded, Whether was it lawfull for the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to ſettle the <hi>Militia</hi> [which is made the cauſe of all our preſent <hi>diſtractions</hi> and <hi>dangers</hi>] or not, without the Kings <hi>Royall</hi> aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Firſt, they did it not without asking his permiſſion and leave; for conſidering the neceſſity of putting the <hi>Kingdome</hi> into a Poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, both in regard of Forreigne and Domeſtick Forces and Foes: they addreſſed themſelves to his Majeſty, deſiring him ſo to order and diſpoſe of the <hi>Militia</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> as it was agreed upon by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112749:3"/>wiſedome of his great and grand <hi>Councell,</hi> whoſe counſell above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>Parliament time,</hi> have, and ought to embrace and follow. And therefore we may imagine that to be lawfull which our beſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, yea Law-makers did ſo earneſtly ſue and ſollicite for.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly the <hi>Parliament</hi> continuing their humble ſupplications unto the <hi>King,</hi> his Majeſtie was once gracioſluy pleaſed by <hi>Meſſage</hi> ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>them,</hi> to promiſe, that the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould be put into ſuch hands as they ſhould approve of, or recommend unto <hi>Him,</hi> provided that they declared [together with the <hi>Names</hi> of the <hi>Perſons</hi>] the <hi>extent</hi> of their <hi>power,</hi> and the time of their continuance, both which they did, which ſhewes evidently; That there was nothing unlawfull in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the thing deſired, [His Majeſty himſelfe not excepting againſt that] but at the moſt, that ſomthing deſired by <hi>them</hi> did not ſquare with ſome <hi>circumſtances</hi> obſerved in former times.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſeeing a neceſſity of ſettling the <hi>Militia,</hi> thought that in <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>humane reaſon</hi> it was much better, fafer, and more agreeable to that truſt which was repoſed in them by the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> That the ſtrength of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> ſhould rather be ordered according to the direction and advice of the <hi>Great Counſell</hi> of the Land equally intruſted by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> for the managing of the great affaires thereof, then that the ſafety of the <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſhould be left at the devotion of a few unknowne Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, many of them having not beene at all formerly intruſted by his Majeſty in any publike office or ſervice, nor confided in by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> And therefore we may conjecture the <hi>legality</hi> of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> ſettled by the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the <hi>Parliament</hi> deſire not to remove the <hi>Militia</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> but from his ſubordinate <hi>Miniſters,</hi> (who by reaſon of their evill counſels given unto <hi>Him,</hi> and their ſmall love, reſpect, and care ſhewed towards <hi>Them</hi>) the <hi>Parliament</hi> dare not confide in; and therefore one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place it upon other Miniſters, whom they have no cauſe to <hi>ſuſpect,</hi> nor againſt whom, (when they were nominated to his Majeſtie) <hi>He</hi> did <hi>except.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, the <hi>Parliament</hi> long ſince ſaw, and ſtill ſees (as <hi>themſelves</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme) the <hi>Kingdome</hi> in ſo evident, and imminent danger, both from enemies abroad; and a popiſh diſcontented, and diſaffected party at home, that there was an urgent, and inevitable neceſſitie of putting the <hi>Kingdome</hi> into a <hi>poſture of defence,</hi> for the ſafeguard both of his Majeſtie and people: and in all probability, and likely hood, if the <hi>Militia</hi> at <hi>Land,</hi> and the <hi>Navy</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> had not been ſetled in ſure hands when they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112749:4"/>were, we had ere this been expoſed to the practiſes of thoſe, who thirſt after the ruine of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and endeavour to kindle that combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>England,</hi> which they have in ſo great a meaſure effected already in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Now <hi>the ſafety of the people being the ſupreame Law,</hi> it muſt needs be <hi>lawfull</hi> for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to ſettle the <hi>Militia,</hi> in caſe of ſuch <hi>neceſſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>6</label> Sixtly, the power given to thoſe, in whoſe hands the <hi>Militia</hi> is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> is onely, to ſuppreſſe Rebellion, <hi>Inſurrection,</hi> and forraigne <hi>Invaſion.</hi> Now that this power ſhould be put into ſome hands is neceſſary, eſpecially in dangerous, and diſtracted times; and into whoſe hands better, and with more ſafety, than ſuch as the <hi>Parliament</hi> dare confide in, and againſt whoſe perſons no exception hath beene taken by his Majeſtie: and therefore we need not much queſtion the <hi>Legality</hi> of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, this is granted on all ſides, to wit, That the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> intruſts the <hi>Parliament</hi> to provide for their <hi>weale,</hi> not for their <hi>woe;</hi> and that this <hi>Parliament</hi> thus intruſted by the <hi>People,</hi> did by a <hi>Law</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the <hi>King</hi> with the <hi>Militia,</hi> to wit, for the weale of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> not for the <hi>woe</hi> thereof: and that this is <hi>implyed</hi> (in that <hi>Act,</hi> or <hi>Grant</hi>) though not <hi>expreſt,</hi> no <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> I perſwade my ſelfe, will queſtion, or deny. And therefore</p>
            <p n="1">I. If the <hi>Kings</hi> deſire, and royall intention be (as we hope it is) to ſettle the <hi>Militia</hi> for the <hi>preſervation,</hi> not <hi>perdition,</hi> for the defence, not <hi>deſtruction,</hi> for the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and ſafety, and not <hi>enflaming,</hi> or <hi>envaſſalling</hi> of his <hi>Subiests,</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> and that this likewiſe is the intent, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of His <hi>Grand Councell,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> then the difference <hi>who ſhall eſtabliſh the Militia,</hi> is but a kinde of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or contention about words, or a ceremony, or a quarrell <hi>who ſhall have their will,</hi> when both purpoſe and reſolve one and the ſame thing: which is to weake a ground, and too triviall a cauſe to draw that ruine, deſolation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon us, which muſt inevitably fall upon, and ceaze us, if theſe <hi>Civill wars</hi> which threaten us, and hang over our heads, be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. But</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>8</label> II. If (which God forbid) the <hi>King</hi> ſhould intend, and endeavour by the ſetling of the <hi>Militia,</hi> to enſlave us, to tirrannize over us, and to rule us (beeing ſo curbed, and kept under by a ſtrong hand of Power) by his owne will, then the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> did never ſettle the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> upon Him for that end, or, to be ſo uſed: for the <hi>equitie</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and not the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is the true <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, it evidently appeares, <hi>Aliquid latet, quod non patet,</hi> That
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112749:4"/>neither the <hi>Militia</hi> ſetled by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor <hi>Hull</hi> kept for the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor the <hi>Magazine of Hull</hi> removed by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> are the true grounds of the <hi>Warre</hi> ſo violently threatned againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> by the malicious, miſcheivous, and malignant partie of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Cavalliers, and other ill-affected perſons. For</p>
            <p n="1">1 There were attempts made to be poſſeſſed of <hi>Hull,</hi> and the <hi>Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine,</hi> by Captaine <hi>Leg,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> before ever Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> was ſeized of it, (much more, before he denied His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie entrance thereinto) and this attempt, deſire, and purpoſe, ſeemes to ſome, (and that not improblably) to take its riſe from the Lord <hi>Digbyes</hi> letter to the <hi>Queene,</hi> wherein he deſires, <hi>That the King would repaire unto ſome place of ſtrength, where he may ſafely protect his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> that is, ſuch as will doe him ſervice againſt his <hi>Parliament, amongſt whom</hi> (moſt diſloyally he ſaith) <hi>Traitors beare ſway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The Lord <hi>Digbie</hi> promiſeth in his Letter unto his Majeſtie before the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſetled <hi>to doe him ſervice abroad,</hi> that is, (as he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf) <hi>to procure for them ſupplies</hi> againſt the Kingdome, and Parliament, with which hee ſaid <hi>himſelfe would returne</hi> (as hee did indeed in the <hi>Ship</hi> called the <hi>Providence,</hi> with ſtore of Armes) although he had been publiſhed, and voted a <hi>Traitour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Before this, the ſame Lord <hi>Digby</hi> endeavoured to raiſe forces, under the pretence of a <hi>Guard</hi> for the <hi>Kings</hi> perſon in winter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Before the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſetled, there were endeavours, to incenſe the two Nations <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to engage their <hi>Armies</hi> one againſt the other, that in ſuch a confuſion, as muſt needs have followed; the <hi>Parliament</hi> might not be able to ſit, nor doe us any good. For if in this <hi>battell</hi> we had been <hi>conquered;</hi> we might have feared to have loſt our ſelves, and all we had, to the <hi>Conquerour with whom we fought;</hi> and if we had <hi>conquered,</hi> we might have been ſure to have loſt our ſelves, and all we had, to the <hi>Malignant Party for whom we fought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Before the ſetling of the <hi>Militia,</hi> there were endeavours to turne the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as is abundantly proved by <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. By the teſtimony, and allegations of many, the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> (which brake forth before the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſetled) was hatched by the popiſh, and diſafected party in <hi>England,</hi> not to have <hi>reſted there,</hi> but to have <hi>ended here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Before the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſetled, ſome Members of both Houſes (who were obſerved to be moſt zealous for the ſpeedy ſuppreſſion of the Iriſh Rebellion, which notwithſtanding, was ſo long protracted and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112749:5"/>delayed) were unjuſtly charged with <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and after ſuch unjuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, were demanded and required of the Houſe of Commons, by His Majeſtie, attended with a <hi>Troope of Cavalliers,</hi> who had intended to have taken them by force, if they had not been abſent. By all which it appeares, That <hi>the ſetling of the Militia</hi> was not the cauſe why <hi>warre</hi> is made upon, or againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much may ſuffice for the <hi>firſt quaere,</hi> concerning <hi>the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſetling of the Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> It may now in the next place be demanded, whether it be lawfull for us to obey this <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>Militia</hi> thus ſetled by <hi>Parliament.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> In caſe of extreame danger, and of his Majeſties refuſall, people are obliged, and ought to obey (by the Fundamentall Laws of this Land) the <hi>Command,</hi> and <hi>Ordinance</hi> agreed upon by <hi>both Houſes,</hi> or the <hi>major part</hi> of <hi>both Houſes</hi> (which is all one) for the <hi>Militia.</hi> I enlarge not this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> becauſe that which followes concerning <hi>the deſerting of the Parliament,</hi> may be applied hereunto.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſuffice for the <hi>firſt exception</hi> taken againſt the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> viz, <hi>Their action,</hi> in putting the Kingdome into a warlike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of defenſe, by ſetling the <hi>Militia</hi> in ſuch hands, as they durſt truſt.</p>
            <p>I proceed now unto the <hi>other Exception,</hi> (viz) the fruits, and effects of the ſetling of the <hi>Militia,</hi> which are affirmed to be, the oppoſing of the <hi>Kings precepts and proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We affirmed before, That if the <hi>Militia</hi> had not been ſettled, we had beene in great danger of deſtruction; and now when it is ſetled we are neither free from feares, nor foes, enemies nor evils. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> Whence it may be demanded, How may we be preſerved from that ruine, and deſtruction which hangs over our heads.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Firſt, by ſtanding upon our Guard.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, by ſiding with and aſſiſting of thoſe who ſtand for us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, by reſiſting and oppoſing thoſe who withſtand us.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Queſtion</hi> is ſomething like <hi>Hydra's heads,</hi> for from this <hi>little Head,</hi> foure <hi>maine ones ſprout</hi> and <hi>ſpring</hi> up; to wit,
<list>
                  <item>1. Whether the <hi>Parliament</hi> may be deſerted, or ought to be aſſiſted?</item>
                  <item>2. Whether the <hi>King</hi> may be diſobeyed, or his Commands oppoſed?</item>
                  <item>3. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">queſt. </seg>4</label> Why the <hi>Parliament</hi> dare not confide in the <hi>King,</hi> ſeeing he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth as much as they can deſire?</item>
                  <item>4. Whether this <hi>Warre</hi> undertaken by the <hi>Parliament</hi> be warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lawfull? Now of all theſe in this order.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It may firſt of all (I ſay) be demanded, Whether we may <hi>deſert</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> in this time of danger, or is it our duty to obey, aſſiſt, aide and ſtick to them.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112749:5"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Firſt, whatſoever is ſaid of this Subject, in that Treatiſe called, <hi>Reaſons why this Kingdome ought to adhere to the Parliament,</hi> I wholy omitt; as alſo many Reaſons which might have beene drawne, from a Trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, which by many ſolide arguments juſtifies <hi>the Scottiſh Subjects for their defenſive warres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, our Saviours rule is here worthy obſervation, <hi>Whatſoever you would, that others ſhould do unto you, doe ſo unto them.</hi> Make the caſe ours, by ſuppoſing us in their places, and <hi>they</hi> in ours, that is, <hi>We</hi> Parliament men, and <hi>they</hi> private perſons; and looke what aide, and aſſiſtance <hi>we</hi> would expect, and deſire from <hi>them,</hi> if <hi>we</hi> were in ſuch danger, as now <hi>they</hi> are, the ſame <hi>we</hi> ſhould now affoord unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, I dare not ſay, that with a blind obedience we ſhould actively obey them in whatſoever they command: for as <hi>Councels</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> ſo <hi>Parliaments</hi> in <hi>Policy,</hi> may erre: and therefore inquiſition, diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, examination, and conference are not forbidden us in any <hi>Acts</hi> or <hi>Statutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> are choſen by us, and ſtand for us, yea, are ſent thither, intruſted by us with all we have, <hi>(viz)</hi> our eſtates, liberties, lives, and the life of our lives, our Religion, and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Kings Perſon, and Honour: and therefore in equity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they ought not to be forſaken of us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> Fiftly the <hi>Parliament men</hi> are no other then <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and therefore we cannot <hi>deſert them,</hi> except we <hi>deſert our ſelves,</hi> the ſafety of the <hi>Commons,</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth</hi> being wrapped up in the ſafety of the <hi>Parliament.</hi> As the <hi>Wolves</hi> deſired the <hi>ſheepe</hi> to put away the <hi>dogs,</hi> and then they would enter into a League with them, but when they had by ſo doing ſtript themſelves of their beſt friends, and laid themſelves open to their fierceſt foes, they were then devoured without pity: even ſo may we feare it will be with us, if we ſhould be ſo ſottiſh as <hi>reject,</hi> and <hi>deſert</hi> the <hi>great, grave,</hi> and <hi>grand Councell of the Land,</hi> (which conſiſts of as wiſe, faithfull, meeke, moderate, ſincere, juſt, upright, underſtanding, zealous, and pious Patriots, as ever any <hi>Parliament</hi> in this Land was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, and conſiſted of) and ſubmit our ſelves to the protection, and care, of obſcure, and unknowne, yea malignant, and malicious Counſellours, who would glory ſo much in nothing as in our miſery, and Ruine, as appeares by their deeds whereſoever they come, if they can but prevaile.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>6</label> Sixtly the <hi>Kings</hi> Majeſtie hath promiſed (in His-Meſſage. January, 12. 1641.) <hi>That He will be as carefull of his Parliament, and of the priviledges thereof, as of his Life, and Crowne,</hi> and therefore if <hi>He</hi> aſſure <hi>them</hi> ſo of His adhering unto, and care of them, then much more ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112749:6"/>
               <hi>we</hi> encourage them, by Promiſing to aſſiſt them (ſo long as they ſtand for us, and our Lawes) with our <hi>eſtates,</hi> and them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, we ought to obey, and aſſiſt them in any thing which is lawfull, and we ought not to ſuſpect, that they will enjoyne, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us any thing as lawfull, which is unlawfull. The oppoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Kings Majeſtie</hi> and His <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſeemes to be about law, He affirming that to be lawfull, which they denie, and they affirming that to be lawfull, which He proclaimes illegall. Now the <hi>King</hi> is pleaſed to profeſſe, That he is no <hi>Expounder of Law,</hi> that belonging nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to His <hi>Perſon,</hi> nor <hi>Office;</hi> and therefore concerning the legality, and illegallity of things, <hi>He</hi> will be guided by the judgement and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of others: And whoſe, or what counſell (in all probability, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) can be better, ſounder, ſincerer, and more worthy to be followed, then that of his <hi>Grand Councell?</hi> who aſſure us that what they doe and enjoyne us to do is <hi>lawfull,</hi> that is, according, and agreeable to the <hi>Law,</hi> either of <hi>God, Nature,</hi> or the Land. Now it becomes <hi>us</hi> (whom they repreſent (thus honourably, and venerably to thinke of <hi>Them, viz,</hi> They know ſuch and ſuch things to be lawfull, and therefore they do them themſelves, and enjoyne them to us. And not thus (as ſome pervert it) The <hi>Parliament</hi> hath done, or commanded ſuch, or ſuch things; and therefore doe affirme them to be lawfull, and juſt: for it is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in law, <hi>That no unworthy, or diſhonourable thing is to be imagined, or preſumed of Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>8</label> Eightly, if we <hi>deſert</hi> and now <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> we ſhall be found guilty before God of three great ſins; to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Perfidiouſneſſe;</hi> for as we have intruſted the <hi>Parliament</hi> with our eſtates, liberties, and lives; ſo we have engaged our ſelves, to maintain, and defend them, ſo long as they purſue our ſafety, proſperitie, preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and peace, according to Law. And therefore, if for our good, or for diſcharging of their conſciences, and truſt, they be endangered, we are perfidious if we leave them, and for lacke of ſuccour let them ſinke and periſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Perjurie;</hi> for all who have taken the PROTESTATION, have promiſed, proteſted, and vowed, with their lives, power, and eſtate, to defend, and maintaine all thoſe who ſtand for the lawfull rights, and liberties of the Subject; yea, to oppoſe, and by all good wayes and meanes to endeavour to bring to condigne puniſhment, all ſuch as ſhall either by force, practiſe, counſels, plots, or otherwiſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or endanger thoſe who ſtand for our Lawes, and Liberties. Now who ſtand more, for our <hi>Religion, Lawes, Soveraigne,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112749:6"/>then our <hi>Parliament?</hi> and who are more oppoſed and endangered for their zeale, and care for <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>our Priviledges</hi> than <hi>They?</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are guilty of <hi>Perjury</hi> before God, and Man, if we in this caſe aſſiſt them not, but <hi>deſert them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Treacherie;</hi> for ſuch as <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the caſe now ſtands, are guilty of a manifold <hi>Treaſon:</hi> to wit, againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> againſt the <hi>State,</hi> againſt the <hi>Repreſentative body</hi> of the Land, and againſt <hi>themſelves.</hi> For by <hi>deſerting</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſuffering it to be trampled under foot, by Papiſts, Atheiſts, prodigals, Delinquents. Antiparliamentaries, and Viperous Monopoliſts, and Projectors; we betray</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Church to errour, and hereſie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The State to ruine, and miſerie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Parliament to bloud, and crueltie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Our ſelves to poverty and ſlavery. And therfore I may truly and boldly ſay, That it is thoſe who <hi>deſert</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who are the Principall cauſes of all the bloud which is, hath, or ſhall beſhed in this <hi>Warre,</hi> and of all the burning, plundering, raviſhing, and theeving, wherewith the poore <hi>Subiect</hi> hath, or ſhall be oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>9</label> Ninthly, we may not vow (when things are come to maturitie and height, and the curſed conception is come to a birth) <hi>deſert</hi> and fall from our <hi>Parliament</hi> becauſe there hath beene long <hi>great jealouſies,</hi> of ſome <hi>greivous miſcheife,</hi> to be intended againſt our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> by thoſe who are enemies to <hi>both.</hi> Here note, that the <hi>jealouſies</hi> which men generally have had, that there was, and is ſtill ſome deſigne a foot, for the ruine and deſtruction of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of us through their ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and of introducing, yea eſtabliſhing of Popery, and of aboliſhing of <hi>Proteſtantiſme</hi> in this Land, are theſe and the like: to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Army of 8000. Iriſh Papiſts, which was raiſed by the Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> and ready to come over, either to further the <hi>Warre</hi> with <hi>Scotland,</hi> or (if that jarre were compoſed) to joyne with the <hi>Engliſh Army</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The endeavours and courſes which were taken, to bring our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Army</hi> out of the <hi>North,</hi> either to deſtroy the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or to awe and compell it, and take away the freedome of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The two Letters ſent to Mr. <hi>Bridgeman, Ian.</hi> 14. 1641. and to Mr. <hi>Anderton,</hi> which intimated ſome ſudden, ſad and ſorrowfull blow to be intended againſt the <hi>Puritanes</hi> in and about the Citie of <hi>London;</hi> and declared many things of deepe and dangerous conſequence, which (conſidering many paſſages in the State ſince) ſeeme not to be faigned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112749:7"/>or forged; but to foretell dangerous and diviliſh practiſes really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt the City, Country, and <hi>Parliament,</hi> by the Popiſh Faction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The accuſing of the 6. worthy <hi>Members of Parliament,</hi> againſt whom (as yet) no proof hath been brought, nor no particular inſtances produced (as hath beene againe, and againe promiſed) of any treachery treaſon or high and treacherous miſdemeanors, practiſes or plotts.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Majeſties going into the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> attended neither with his ordinary <hi>Gaurd,</hi> only, nor <hi>Pentioners</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> only but with diverſe <hi>Cavaliers armed</hi> who by their words and geſtures ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves to bee men of deſperate reſolutions and bent them upon ſome damnable, and bloody deſigne.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The endeavours uſed to the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Innes</hi> of <hi>Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was raiſed for the diverſion and interruption of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the weakning of our Land, by the maintenance of that, and for the ſtrengthening of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Faction</hi> with us. For when the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> had beene plundered, pillaged, ſubdued and ſlaughtered there, (as it was reported, confeſſed and acknowledged by divers of the <hi>Rebels,</hi> when they were taken) they ſhould have come hither to have aſſiſted our <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Malignants,</hi> to have done as much to and with us.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The calling in diverſe <hi>Cannoneers,</hi> and other <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> into the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. The making of <hi>Lunsford</hi> (a man of a knowne and notorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach'd life and converſation) <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the <hi>Tower;</hi> for he being ſo apt and fit a man for any deſperate deſigne, or divelliſh practiſe, and in that place, having ſo much command over the <hi>City,</hi> made all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally feare, that there was more miſchiefe intended againſt the <hi>City,</hi> then did outwardly appeare.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The ſelling of the <hi>Crowne Jewels</hi> beyond the Seas, and buying therewith <hi>Field-pieces, Pieces</hi> for <hi>Battery, Culverings, Morter-peices, Carabines, Piſtols, Warre-ſaddles, Swords</hi> and <hi>Powder,</hi> as appeared by the note of direction which was ſent over, and found among the <hi>Lord Digbies</hi> Papers. Now although theſe were bought in <hi>June;</hi> yet we muſt imagine (as appeares by the time when they were writ for) that they were beſpoke, and that order was given for the providing of them long before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fortifying and guarding of <hi>Whitehall</hi> with <hi>Amuunition,</hi> in an unuſuall manner, and with men of turbulent ſpirits; for ſome of them with provoking language and violence abuſed divers Citizens paſſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112749:7"/>by; and others with their ſwords drawne wounded ſundry other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens paſſing by (who we unarmed) in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. The drawing away of many <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> by Meſſages and Letters from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> That the <hi>Actions</hi> of both <hi>Houſes</hi> might be blemiſhed and reported to be the <hi>Votes</hi> onely of a few, and an inconſiderable number, yea rather the <hi>Acts of a Party,</hi> then of a <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. The <hi>force</hi> raiſed at <hi>Yorke,</hi> and the <hi>Ammunition</hi> provided beyond <hi>Sea,</hi> for to be ſent unto <hi>Yorke</hi> that <hi>force</hi> being gathered (as was feared) to make an oppoſition againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but evidently percieved to be imployed for the protection, and <hi>ſupport</hi> of <hi>Delinquents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The multiplying of <hi>Papiſts</hi> in this Land of late dayes their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent meetings at certaine places in and about the <hi>City</hi> without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule, the audaciouſneſſe of their <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our ſtrict and ſevere <hi>Statutes</hi> againſt <hi>them,</hi> the reſidence of the <hi>Popes Nunntio</hi> ſo long amongſt us, the <hi>Colledge of Capuchins</hi> in or nere unto <hi>Coven Garden,</hi> and the favouring and prefering principally ſuch as were either <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or <hi>Armini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> who in ſome points are true <hi>Cozen Germanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. Laſtly his <hi>Majeſties</hi> abſenting of <hi>himſelfe</hi> from his <hi>Parliament,</hi> withdrawing from <hi>them</hi> thereby both his <hi>preſence</hi> and influence. Here note That after the <hi>King</hi> was councelled, and perſwaded hereunto, this his <hi>abſence</hi> followed and attended with this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> againe and againe <hi>iterated, viz. That the King abſenting; diſſenting, and ſevering of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from his Parliament, it was no Parliament neither had they any Power to diſpoſe of any of the weightie affaires of the Kingdome; which</hi> dangerous <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſeemes to have beene taught by <hi>Court flatterers</hi> for theſe ends <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To diſcourage, weary and quite tire out our couragious, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable <hi>Senate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To divert, interupt and retard their conſultations, and deſignes both for our owne <hi>Reformation,</hi> and the <hi>ſubduing</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To take off peoples hearts from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to ſtagger them in their obedience unto them, to coole their zeale for the preſervation and defence of them, and to make them call in queſtion all their proceedings</p>
            <p n="4">4. To annimate all thoſe who ſtood diſaffected to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to ſhow their diſaffection, and oppoſion with more freedome and leſſe feare.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, and laſtly to this maine queſtion, <hi>whether the Parliament may be deſerted or ought to be adhered unto,</hi> I anſwere that of (of neceſſity)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112749:8"/>ſome wee muſt adhere and ſtick unto, that is either to the grand and knowne Councellours of the Land, or to obſcure and private Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, that is either to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or to the <hi>Cavalliers, Papiſts, Malignants, Delinquents</hi> and <hi>diſſaffected Perſons</hi> of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe <hi>Contraria jnxta ſe poſita clarius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luceſcunt,</hi> contraries are beſt commentaries, wee will looke particularly upon both and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>nature, ends and aimes of both,</hi> and from thence coniecture whom wee may beſt deſert, and whom with moſt ſafety <hi>follow;</hi> and firſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the <hi>Cavalliers,</hi> and that ſide.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in that <hi>ſide</hi> which conſiſts of <hi>Cavalliers, Papiſts, Malignants, Del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquents, ill-affected and Popiſhly affeted Perſons,</hi> or (to terme them onely ſo) <hi>evill, private and obſcure Councellors,</hi> wee have theſe two things to obſerve, to wit; Firſt, their intentions and endeavours: Secondly, their nature and ends.</p>
            <p>Firſt, their intentions, endevours and the fruit of their Councells; for I conioyne them altogether.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their intentions and endevours were to raiſe <hi>Civill Warre,</hi> and that both firſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and afterwards in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and now in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. To perſwade the <hi>King</hi> to rule by his owne <hi>Will.</hi> The Lord <hi>Faulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> tels us, That <hi>the King was perſwaded by his Divines that in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by his Councellours that in policie, and by his Judges that by law he might doe what he liſt.</hi> Which doth directly labour to raze the very foundation of our well founded State, and to introduce and reare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us an <hi>Arbitrary Government.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="3">3. They endeavour to make diviſion betweene his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his <hi>Parliament,</hi> (whom God and the Lawes of this Land have united in ſo neere a relation) as appeares.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By their endeavours and perſwaſions to draw the <hi>King</hi> from his <hi>Parliament,</hi> which they have effected now for a long time, and ſtill continues his abſence from <hi>them;</hi> although (I thinke) the moſt <hi>Shires</hi> in <hi>England</hi> have moſt humbly petitioned and beſought <hi>Him</hi> to rejoyce and revive all the drooping, dead and ſad hearts of <hi>his People,</hi> by affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his much and long deſired <hi>preſence,</hi> unto his <hi>Parliament.</hi> If theſe <hi>Perſons</hi> (whatſoever they are) who thus counſell the <hi>King</hi> to eſtrange himſelfe from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to oppoſe and diſguſt all their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,</hi> and deſignes, were but Maſters of <hi>Hull,</hi> the <hi>Militia,</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> they would then quickly <hi>maſter</hi> both the <hi>Parliament</hi> and all the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> who could expect but bad quarter from ſuch <hi>Maſters,</hi> who by their counſels and endeavours to divide the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112749:8"/>ſhew that they are neither <hi>friends</hi> to the <hi>Common wealth,</hi> nor <hi>favourers</hi> of the <hi>publique ſafety;</hi> And</p>
            <p>Secondly, By their feare that the King ſhould accord with his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> For the <hi>Malignants</hi> and evill <hi>Counſellours</hi> ſtand in great feare That his Majeſty is too inclinable to an accommodation with his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which above all things they abhor fearing thereby to be <hi>undone,</hi> that is, to loſe the ſpoile, pillage and poſſeſſions of this Land, which they have long ſince hoped for: whence they have ſolicited the <hi>Queene</hi> to diſſwade the <hi>King</hi> by all meanes from ſuch <hi>accommodation,</hi> hoping to obtaine their deſires (the ruine of this Land) by the <hi>Queenes</hi> interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. See the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> Letter to the Queene, <hi>March</hi> 10. 1641. and Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> Letter to the Lord <hi>Digby. May</hi> 27. 1642.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They endeavour to caſt <hi>aſperſions</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>People,</hi> That the <hi>Parliament</hi> would ſet up a <hi>Ariſtocracie,</hi> take away the Law, and introduce an arbitrary government; a report ſo falſe that no man of common ſenſe or reaſon can credit it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They have and doe ſtill endeavour and combine together to effect end worke the ruine of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or at leaſt to force it, and by forcing thereof to cut up the freedome of <hi>Parliament</hi> by the root, and either to take all <hi>Parliaments</hi> away, or (which is worſe) make them the inſtruments of ſlavery, to confirme it by Law, as the <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>Rich.</hi> 2nds. time did, when they found the Kings anger againſt them, and feared the peoples forſaking of them. See the Treatiſe called, The ſucceſſe of former <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The fruits and effects of the intentions, and indeavours of thoſe <hi>evill Counſellours,</hi> have been nothing but contention, diſſention, diviſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, decay of trading, and more miſery then would fill a volume, if we ſhould conſider all the diſtractions diſtreſſes, dangers, feares, diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, hinderances, and loſſes, which both <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have felt, undergone, and ſuſtained by their counſels, deſignes, and plots.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the <hi>Intentions,</hi> and <hi>indeavours,</hi> of <hi>evill counſellors,</hi> and the <hi>fruits,</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of their <hi>evill counſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we have now to conſider, the <hi>nature,</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> of theſe <hi>evill counſellours,</hi> who <hi>deſert,</hi> and <hi>oppoſe</hi> the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They are men of loſt eſtates, and deſperate fortunes; and theſe aime onely at plundering, and pillaging, deſiring to raiſe themſelves by razing others, and to build no themſelves upon their brethrens ruine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and popiſhly affected perſons. The Citizens of <hi>London</hi> (in their petition preſented to the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 11. 1641. teſtifie. That information is given to divers of them, from all parts of the Kingdome, of the bold and inſolent carriage, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112749:9"/>ſpeeches of the Papiſts. Now thoſe aime either at the introducing and eſtabliſhing of Popery amongſt us, by the change of religion, or at leaſt, at the gaining of freedome to profeſſe, or an open to leration of their idolatrous, and ſuperſtitious religion. Which becauſe they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver expect, nor hope for, from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (which labours ſo ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly for the reformation of our Church, and the abolition of all pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and popiſh innovations) they therefore joyne, and ſide with the former ſort, which ſeeke nothing but miſcheife and ruine. Or</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are Delinquents, Malefactors, and guilty Perſons, who have by ſome plotts, practiſes, monopolies, Projects, or otherwiſe, treſpaſſed and tranſgreſſed highly againſt the Common-wealth for their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate advantage and profit. Now theſe hope, that by ſiding with the <hi>Cavaleirs</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they ſhall bee protected againſt it and the juſtice thereof. Or</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are the miniſters of the Land, who are corrupt either in Life or Doctrine; that is, are either ſuperſtitious, ceremonious, contentious, covetous, Popiſh hereticall ſcandalous in their lives and converſations of ſlothfull in the diſcharge of the worke of their miniſtry. Now theſe hope by ſiding with the former, to keepe, and hold faſt what they have fearing the juſtice of the Parliaments will (for their demerrits) deprive them of thoſe ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall dignities and poſſeſſions which they hold and injoy; Or,</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are of that number of the Nobility or Gentry of the Land, whoſe lives have been very looſe, &amp; unbridled. Now theſe oppoſe the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proceedings of the Parliament, leaſt ſuch reſtraint ſhould be impoſed upon them by that Reformation which is intended and indeavoured by <hi>Them</hi> that they may (without punniſhment) live as they liſt, have done and deſire ſtill to doe; Or</p>
            <p n="6">6. They are ignorant Perſons. Now there is a two fold ignorance <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Naturall; now they are naturally ignorant who for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge underſtanding, and teaching are neither able to diſcerne of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and intentions, of the <hi>adverſe Partie,</hi> nor to foreſee the miſeries which will come upon them by aiding and aſſiſting of, and ſiding with them: nor to know what is their duty and how farre and in what caſes they may aid and aſſiſt the Parliament againſt ſome <hi>perſonall or verball command</hi> of the King; And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Affected:</hi> Now this miſchevous, malitious, and affected <hi>ignorance</hi> is in thoſe who will neither read, nor heare any thing which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them in the former particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> the nature intentions ends and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112749:9"/>fruites of evill councels, and counſellours: and what is their duty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the great counſel of the land. Or,</p>
            <p n="7">7. They are of that number of the Nobility, and Gentry, who ſeeke preferment by betraying their Country, to ſerve, and be made ſubject to the Court. Or.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They are the allyes, friends, acquaintance, and aſſociates of ſome of the former; who although in themſelves they ſtand not much diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> yet in regard of their friends, they leave it, and cleave unto them. Or,</p>
            <p n="9">9. They are timerous and fearefull: who although they wiſh well unto the <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet they dare not ſhew their affection, nor affoord any aid unto them, leſt thereby they incurre ſome malice, or detriment through the Kings diſpleaſure, Or.</p>
            <p n="10">10. They are covetous, and deſirous to keepe their mony, and meanes: and therefore (whatſoever their heart, and affections be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Parliament</hi>) they dare not ſhew their approbation of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, leſt they ſhould be wrought upon to ſupply them, and their wants, for the ſupporr of the <hi>State,</hi> their neceſſities, and occaſions, in regard of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>land,</hi> being great, urgent, and preſſing. Or,</p>
            <p n="11">11. They are <hi>Macchiavillians,</hi> and <hi>Polititions;</hi> who deſiring with the <hi>Cat</hi> to fall on their feet, and to be free from blame and danger how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the world wags, will neither ſide, nor ſupport, neither aid, nor aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, either <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now ſeriouſly conſider three things from what hath beene ſaid of the nature of this <hi>Side,</hi> or <hi>Party, viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt. who are thoſe <hi>evill Counſellours</hi> which we muſt not <hi>adhere</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but <hi>deſert?</hi> It is denyed, <hi>That there are any ſuch about the King;</hi> but I conceive, what I ſhall <hi>ſay,</hi> will not be <hi>gainſayd, viz.</hi> If there bee any about the King, who firſt move him to <hi>Civill warres,</hi> and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perſwade him to rule his people according to his owne <hi>Will,</hi> or an <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power,</hi> and thirdly, ſtrive to divide, and eſtrange the King from his <hi>Parliament,</hi> and fourthly, caſt (even in his eares) <hi>aſpertions,</hi> and falſe calumnies upon his <hi>Parliament,</hi> and fiftly, labour to ruine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſixthly, by their plots brings miſery and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the <hi>whole land:</hi> none (I ſay) will deny, but theſe are evill and wicked Counſellours, who deſerve to be diſclaimed, deſerted, and left free, and layd open to the penalty of the <hi>law.</hi> Now that there are ſome ſuch about the <hi>King,</hi> or in high favour, power and credit with <hi>Him,</hi> is more then evident (though I, and wiſer then I, cannot parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly name them) for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Majeſty profeſſeth a deteſtation of warre, and yet proſecutes it,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112749:10"/>which ſhewes that ſome puts him upon it. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. He proteſts to governe his people according to eſtabliſhed law, and yet he hath been perſwaded to an <hi>Arbitrary governement,</hi> by them about <hi>Him,</hi> by many plauſible, and faire ſeeming arguments, as Himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes in one of his Meſſages. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſolemnely profeſſeth his love unto, and his care of, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable reſpect to his <hi>Parliaments</hi> and their priviledges, and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and yet ſome hath withdrawne his perſon from the Parliament, and to himſelfe, vilified the Parliament, yea have had plots upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and have laboured that in them, they might be <hi>countenanced,</hi> and <hi>protected</hi> by his <hi>ſacred Majeſty,</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>King</hi> againe and againe calleth God to witneſſe, the ſincerity of his heart towards all his people, and how earneſtly deſirous He is that they may live happily, and proſperouſly under him; and yet by following the counſell of ſome, many, great, and long evills have preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the three Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And therefore it muſt needes be granted, <hi>That there are malignant Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours about the King, who worke much miſery, and miſchiefe, both to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felfe and his People;</hi> and that they cannot be unknowne unto <hi>Him,</hi> if <hi>He</hi> would pleaſe to diſcloſe, diſcover, and leave them to the juſt, and equall triall of the <hi>Lovers</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, let us conſider from this <hi>Army of Malignants,</hi> and <hi>miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Counſellours,</hi> and <hi>party,</hi> what in all probability we may expect, and looke for if they prevaile againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi> That is, if,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Men of deſperate fortunes prevaile, what can we expect but plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and pillaging? And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Papiſts prevaile, what religion but Popery?</p>
            <p n="3">3. If delinquents, what but oppreſſion?</p>
            <p n="4">4. If bad Miniſters, what but bad preaching, and ill practizing?</p>
            <p n="5">5. If looſe Gentry, what but prophanneſſe?</p>
            <p n="6">6. If ambitious ſpirits, what but contempt, cruelty, and diſdaine?</p>
            <p n="7">7. If ignorant perſons, what but their owne ſelfe-wills?</p>
            <p n="8">8. If delinquents and malignants friends, what but ſuch a meaſure as we finde from delinquents, and malignants themſelves? But from an <hi>Army</hi> conſiſting not of <hi>one,</hi> but of <hi>all theſe,</hi> what can we expect, but <hi>all theſe evills?</hi> and from the wickedneſſe which will be committed by them, the heavy judgment of God to be haſtened downe upon us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let us conſider, whether there be any the leaſt probability of receiving any benefit, or profit, in any regard, from this <hi>Side</hi> or <hi>Party,</hi> if they ſhould prevaile againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Can we expect that the propriety of our goods ſhall be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112749:10"/>and preſerved unto us, by men of decayed, loſt, and deſperate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes? Or,</item>
               <item>2. Can we expect that the true orthodoxe Proteſtant Religion ſhall be maintained, and preſerved, by heterodoxe, and hereticall Papiſts? Or,</item>
               <item>3. Can we expect to be preſerved free from unjuſt impoſitions, and taxes, by oppreſſing Projectors, and Monopoliſts? Or,</item>
               <item>4. Can we hope that our <hi>Parliament, priviliges</hi> will be preſerved by <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and <hi>contemners</hi> of <hi>Parliaments?</hi> Or,</item>
               <item>5. Can we expect the propagation of the Goſpel, or that the ſincere, faithfull, painfull, and profitable preaching thereof, ſhall be promoted by lewd, lazy, and corrupt Miniſters? Or,</item>
               <item>6. Can we expect that Piety, and the honour of God, ſhall be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the land, by looſe and prophane Gentlemen, and Nobles? Or,</item>
               <item>7. Can we expect that juſtice, juſt meaſure, and equity, ſhall be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by thoſe who ayme at nothing but their owne gaine, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Or,</item>
               <item>8. Can we expect that our Lawes ſhall be preſerved inviolably, by thoſe who are wholely bewitched with the love of an <hi>Arbitrary, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement?</hi> Senſe, and Reaſon will tell us, that <hi>theſe things</hi> cannot be expected from <hi>thoſe perſons;</hi> neither that any good can come unto the Land from ſuch an <hi>Army.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I might conclude this laſt Anſwer, to that maine Queſtion, <hi>Whether the Parliament be to be obeyed or deſerted?</hi> as I began it: to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>
               </label> To our <hi>Side</hi> of neceſſity we muſt adhere and cleave, that is, either to the <hi>evill,</hi> and <hi>obſcure Counſellours,</hi> or to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt not adhere and ſticke to the <hi>evill</hi> and <hi>malignant ones,</hi> for thoſe reaſons ſpecified before.</p>
            <p>Therefore we muſt adhere and cleave cloſe to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This argument (I ſay) together with what hath been ſpoken againſt the <hi>Malignant party,</hi> might be ſufficient for the amplification of the laſt Anſwer: but as I have ſaid ſomthing <hi>againſt</hi> the one <hi>party,</hi> ſo I will ſay ſomething <hi>for</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> as I promiſed, for the better faſtning and ſetting of the <hi>Truth</hi> home upon the heart, of whoſoever will vouchſafe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe this <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that <hi>Side,</hi> or <hi>party,</hi> which conſiſts of the <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>grand Councell</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> I will (as in the other <hi>Party</hi> obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divers things, for the amplification of this truth, <hi>That the Parliament ought not to be deſerted, but obeyed, and aſſiſted:</hi> to wit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The ends of Parliaments.</item>
               <item>2. Their neceſſity.</item>
               <item>3. Their excellency.</item>
               <item>4. Their utility.</item>
               <item>5. The reaſon why we ought to believe <hi>ours.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112749:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>ends</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> are brieſly theſe two: to wit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the intereſt of the people might be ſatisfied.</item>
               <item>2. That the King might be better counſelled.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhewes it ſelfe by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and diſtreſſed condition wherein our <hi>Land</hi> was, and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of agrievances we groaned under; as is to the life declared, in the <hi>Parlioments Remonſtrance of the State of the Kingdome,</hi> ſet forth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 15. 1641.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Excellency</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> is declared by his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> himſelfe, who doth highly extoll the conſtitution of this Governement of ours, and eſpecially the nature of our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> which conſiſt of <hi>King, Peeres,</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> acknowledging that the power which is legally placed in <hi>both Houſes,</hi> is more then ſufficient to prevent end reſtraine the power of tyranny. Which argues plainely, that there is much, and great power, (and that by <hi>Law</hi>) placed, and put into the hands of <hi>both Houſes,</hi> or the <hi>Major part</hi> of <hi>both</hi> for the good, and preſervation of <hi>Peeres,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> when the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or <hi>Whole</hi> is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the <hi>King</hi> being ſeduced by wicked Connſell, doth deſert, and refuſe to joyne with them in their owne defence. For if <hi>they</hi> cannot do any thing (upon anp occaſion, neceſſity, extremity, or danger, though never ſo evident, apparent, or urgent) without the <hi>King,</hi> then the ſole power of managing the affaires of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> doth even <hi>in arduis, in high,</hi> yea in the <hi>higheſt</hi> caſes, belonging onely unto the <hi>King;</hi> and nothing at all to <hi>either,</hi> or <hi>both Houſes,</hi> except, or but what he alleages. That is, though the <hi>Land</hi> ſay a bleeding, and were invaded by Hoaſts, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies from abroad, and Papiſts, and Rebells at home (<hi>Ireland</hi> now is) and the <hi>King</hi> would make no proviſion againſt them, or, for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and withſtanding of them, the <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt ſit ſtill, and ſuffer all to be loſt, and ruined, having neither power to raiſe, nor uſe any force without the <hi>thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Vtility,</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> is great: and that both,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To Kings, and Princes; and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of their reputation, ſame, and honour. <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> is greatly renowned for communicating all weighty affaires, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publike advice, and approbation in all great expedients of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments; and <hi>He</hi> was more honourable, and proſperous therein, then was <hi>Nero,</hi> who made his owne <hi>will</hi> his <hi>Law.</hi> And thus alwaies thoſe Princes have gained unto themſelves moſt honour and renowne, who were moſt willing and ready to liſten to the Counſell of the Land in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant affaires. And alſo</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112749:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of their Crowne, ſtate; for the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by this <hi>repreſentative Body</hi> of their <hi>People,</hi> are alwayes aſſiſted, and that upon all occaſions: as for example.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If they lack money for any neceſſary occaſion, the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſupplies them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if they be invaded by any forraigne or domeſtique foe, or force, the <hi>Parliament</hi> aſſiſts them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if they be injured, reproched or diſhonored by any potent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Prince, the <hi>Parl.</hi> wil vindicate and avenge them. All which were ſeene evidently in Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, between her and her <hi>Parliament,</hi> And</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I may ad, that none of our Princes were ever yet happy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe of <hi>Parliaments:</hi> and therefore it is plaine that they are bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall &amp; utile unto Princes, and conſequently not to be deſerted of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which are loyall to Princes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As <hi>Parliaments</hi> are uſefull and <hi>utile</hi> to <hi>Princes,</hi> ſo they are alſo <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall</hi> and <hi>profitable</hi> unto <hi>People:</hi> as appears by 3. particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Without <hi>Parliaments</hi> People have no poſſibility of pleading their own rights, &amp; liberties, they being too confuſed a body to appear in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of their proper intereſts. Whence it comes frequently to paſſe, that what all ſhould look after, no man does, and what is committed to no man thinks his owne charge: and therfore ſome few choſen out by, and from amongſt the People, to conſider of their liberties, lawes and grievances, muſt needs be very advantagious unto them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As people cannot without confuſion plead for themſelves, ſo often the ſubordinate Magiſtrates, and Iudges of the Land (through feare, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or private corruptions) doe often betray the peoples rights, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſentences or verdicts: and therefore ſuch Counſellours as can have no private aymes, or ends of their owne; but are themſelves involved in the ſame condition with the people, both in weale, and woe muſt needs be profitable for them. Yea,</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> we have reaped already many great, and notable benefits; and therfore may conclude from our owne ezperience, with a <hi>Probatum eſt, That Parliaments are beneficiall to people.</hi> By this <hi>Parliament</hi> we are free from theſe two grievous arbitrary Courts, the high <hi>Commiſſion:</hi> (the <hi>Purgatory</hi> of the Church) and <hi>Satr-chamber,</hi> (the terrour of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi>) as alſo from the heavy burthen of <hi>Ship-money,</hi> and the oppreſſions we groaned under by reaſon of <hi>Meno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies,</hi> and other illegall impoſitions, yea <hi>Biſhops</hi> removed out of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peeres,</hi> who having their dependance upon the <hi>King,</hi> for the moſt part would ſide with him, in any thing, though it were adjudged by the <hi>Parliament</hi> to be deſtructive and hurtfull to the Kingdome. This
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112749:12"/>particular is ſo abundantly amplified, and that ſo truely, by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in their <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of the ſtate of the Kingdom, ſet forth <hi>Dec.</hi> 15. 1641. that I will not enlarge it; but only conclude, that if the <hi>ends, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, excellency,</hi> and <hi>benefits</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> be ſuch as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then <hi>They</hi> are worth ſtanding for, and ought not to be <hi>deſerted.</hi> Now</p>
            <p>Fiftly, we will take a ſhort view of ſome particular reaſons why we ought ta beleeve, &amp; obey this our preſent <hi>Parl.</hi> and not relinquiſh it. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they can have no by ends, nor baſe reſpects of their own: for if they aimed at promotion, preferment, and wealth, they might much eaſilier attaine thoſe, by complying with, then by oppoſing the deſignes and perſonall commands of the King. It is (or at leaſt hath been) an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <hi>Maxim, that a community can have no private ends to miſlead it, and to make it injurious to it ſelfe:</hi> and I never heard nor read ſo much as one ſtory of any <hi>Parl.</hi> freely elected and held, that ever (for any ends of their own) did injure a whole <hi>kingdom,</hi> or exerciſe any tyranny over the land (but divers <hi>Kings</hi> have done ſundry acts of oppreſſion) for nothing can ſuit or ſquare with the <hi>common Councell,</hi> but only the <hi>common good,</hi> and therfore it is great reaſon that we ſhould beleeve &amp; obey them. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe no benefit at all can redound unto them by faigning, forging, or counterfeiting of falſe fires, feares, chymera's, and dangers which are not. And therfore we may they better beleeve what they ſay. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe we never yet found them falſe uuto us. It was the ſaying of one, <hi>If my friend deceive me once, I wil blame him, but if twice, my ſelf;</hi> meaning, that he would never truſt him the ſecond time, who deceived him once. Now charity perſwades us to hope, aud believe, where we ſee nothing to the contrary; and give credit to them in whom we never ſaw any deſignes or indeavours, to betray us, or our liberties, but rather al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the contrary. And,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe they know more then any one of us. <hi>Two eyes</hi> (we ſay) <hi>ſees more then one;</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> is the eies, and the eares of the re-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and their information, conference intelligence, experience, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp;c. doth afford unto them ſome ſight and inſight into all things, paſſages, occaſions, affaires, negotiations, &amp;c. both at home and abroad. And therfore it is not without cauſe, that we ſhould beleeve them. And</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe they never ſhewed any diſloyalty unto the King, that ever yet was obſerved by the <hi>Commons</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> whom they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. We find in all their Petitions, royall expreſſions, humble ſuits, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty intreaties unto his <hi>Ma:</hi> to comply with them for his owne honour &amp; ſafety, cordiall Poteſtations of the ſincerity of their intentions towards his Ma: and free and full promiſes neither to ſpare pains, purſes, perſons, nor eſtates, for the defence of his perſon, &amp; preſervation of his honor; yea unwearied &amp; (beyond humane patience) continued ſupplications to his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112749:12"/>notice of perſonall imputations, yea reproachfull aſperſions, that hath bin caſt upon them; ſtill taking (as much as poſsibly they can) all blam from his Majeſty, and laying it upon his evill counſell. And</p>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe the King himſelfe doth not accuſe the Parliament, but onely ſome few particular perſons therein; and therefore that which comes, or is commended unto us by the whole Parliament, we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and obey, his Majeſty promiſing to protect them, and their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and to except them in all his taxes, and accuſations. And,</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly we may believe, obey, and adhere unto the Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King of Kings ſeemes to favour their proceedings. How doe we ſee the Lord blowing upon all the devices of their enemies, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times turning them back upon themſelves, and ſometimes turning their wiſedome into fooliſhneſſe. Or what counſels, what letters, what plots, and practiſes, what words, and paſſages, againſt Kingdome and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath ſtrangely been diſcovered, prevented, and come to light, to the joy and rejoycing of Parliament and people, and the terrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement of the contrivers, and authors of them. How extraordinarily hath the Lord aſſiſted that honourable Aſſembly with zeale, courage, wiſedome, diſcretion, prudence, moderation, patience, and conſtancy in all their conſultations and deſires? How hath the Lord preſerved their Perſons from imminent perill, and given them favour in the eyes of all Counties, notwithſtanding the baſe, and bitter aſperſions caſt upon them by ſome? When they had cauſe to be diſcouraged, by reaſon of the ſtrong oppoſition of Delinquents, and diſaffected perſons, what encouragments have they even then found, from the Petitions, Promiſes, and reſolutions, of divers Shires? Wherefore, ſeeing theſe are bleſſings, and ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto the godly, we may perſwade our ſelves, that the Lord ſeeing the ſincerity of their intentions, doth in much mercy ſhew his gratious acceptation of their zeale, for the good of our Church, King, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. I conclude this particular, if the Lord ſeeme to ſay to our grave, and gratioos Senators, as he ſaid unto <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.5, 6</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall be none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to withſtand you, becauſe I will be with you, yea, I will not leave you, nor forſake you; therfore be ſtrong, and of good courage:</hi> then let none who would be the Lords ſouldiers, and ſervants, deſert the horſemen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Chariots thereof, yea the Lords Captains who fight his battels.</p>
            <p>And thus by a ſerious conſideration of theſe grounds, we may eaſily conjecture, yea abundantly ſatisfie our ſelves in this point, That the Parl. is not to be deſerted, or forſaken by us. I proceed now unto the next Quaere, which is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> Whether may the King be diſobeyed, and his commands withſtood, or not? Whether He is to be oppoſed in his proceedings by any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112749:13"/>of the Parl. Or whether are we now to obey King or Parliament?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, ſome Princes think, that they may lawfully do, whatſoever they have power to do, or can do; but the contrary ſeems truer (both by light of reaſon, religiou, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l power intruſted by law in the hands of any) <hi>viz.</hi> that Princes have no power to do, but what is lawful, and ſit to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2,</label> Secondly, perſonall actions of ſuperiours be diſobeyed. The <hi>Gramari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſay, <hi>Rex regis, à rego,</hi> the word <hi>King</hi> comes from <hi>Governing,</hi> becauſe <hi>Kings</hi> are no other, but more <hi>high,</hi> and <hi>ſupreme Governours,</hi> and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</hi> Now ſome hold (and I think warrantably) that if any Magiſtrate, or Judge, do purſue a man, not judicially, and by order of Law, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade him by violence without any juſt cauſe againſt all law, that then in ſo doing he is to be held as a private perſon, and as ſuch we may defend our ſelves againſt him. As for example, a woman may defend her ſelfe own body againſt an adulterer, though a Magiſtrate. A ſervant may hold his Maſters hands, if he ſeek to kill wife, or children in his rage. Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Paſſengers may reſiſt him who ſtands at helme, if they ſee that he would run the ſhip againſt a rock; yea they might hold the Princes hands, if being at the helme he miſgoverns the ſhip, to theia certain ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, without prevention, becauſe by his ſo governing thereof, He haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards both his owne life, and theirs, and they by holding of his hands, prevent both his, and their own ruine, (which ſeems to be our preſent caſe) and therefore, much more may the <hi>whole Body</hi> defend it ſelf againſt any ſuch unjuſt and unlawfull invaſion, as will indanger the ſafety, and welfare of all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the Kings perſonall, that is verball commands, without any ſtamp of his anthority upon them, and againſt the <hi>order</hi> of <hi>both Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> I imagiue may be diſobeied. For I do conceive that no lawyer will ſay, that ſuppoſe the King ſhould take the <hi>broad Seal of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> from the Lord Keeper, into his own hands, that all the writs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſhould iſſue forth ſigned with his own hand, and ſealed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ought to be obeyed: for it is not the ſtamp and impreſſion of the Seale which makes a thing lawfull, but the Keeper thereof ought to be a Lawyer, and (by his place) ſhould not for feare, or favour, ſigne any Writs there with, but ſuch as are legall, and if he do otherwiſe, he is lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be queſtioned, and cenſured by a Parliament. And therefore doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, when Writs and Precepts are iſſued forth without the <hi>broad ſeal,</hi> or without a regall, that is, legall authority (as of all the Writs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, for executing the Commiſſion of Array, are, as is proved both by the Parliament and others) they may be diſobeyed, and withſtood, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when they are deſtructive to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112749:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Princes by Parliaments may be withſtood, when they deſire, or endeavour thoſe things, which tend to the envaſſailing of their people. Kings (we know) ſometimes have loved their enemies more then their friends, and have marched forth amongſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to encounter with their friends. As for example, <hi>Richard</hi> 2. thought <hi>Spencor,</hi> and his confederates his beſt friends, though they were baſe ſycophants, and bainefull foes, and conceited that his Peers (who were his loyalleſt Subjects) were the trueſt Traitors, And hence Princes being abuſed by the ſlattery of private perſons (for ſome wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ends of their own) have followed their private perverſe counſels, before the grave, loyall and faithfull advice of their ſage Senate. Now that it is lawfull for Parliaments to withſtand Princes, who make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Warre upon their people, is ſo evidently proved, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that lately come forth, and learned and pious Treatiſe, called, <hi>A Soveraigne Antidote to prevent Civill Warres,</hi> Pag. 6, 7, 8, 9, &amp;c. that at preſent I wholy ſilence it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, the matter with us is quite, and generally miſtaken, and the Queſtion altogether wrong ſtated, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether we ſhould obey the King, or Parliament? for the King and Parliament are not like two parallell lines, which can never meet, nor like two incompatible qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which cannot be both in one ſubject, nor like the Arke and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, whom one Houſe will not hold, nor like God and Mammon, which one man cannot ſerve; for by ſiding with, and aſſiſting of the Parliament, in thoſe things which are according to Law, we ſide with, and ſerve the King.</p>
            <p>Two things are here diſtinguiſhable, to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In our obeying of the Parliament according to Law, we obey the King. This his Majeſty grants, commands and commends, yea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that he requires no obedience of us to himſelfe, farther then he enjoynes that which is Law, lawfull and juſt, And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In our obeying of the Parliament in this preſent <hi>Military</hi> and <hi>Martiall deſigne,</hi> we ſtand for the King, not againſt Him: that is, for the good of his ſoule, perſon, eſtate, honour and poſterity; of which a word or two ſeverally.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſtand for the Soule of their Soveraigne, who withſtand him (having a lawfull call, and warrant thereunto) from doing thoſe things which (if he doe) he can never juſtifie in the Court of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor at the great chancery day of Judgement, but muſt ſinke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſentence of condemnation, for thoſe unlawfull, and unjuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able facts. And therefore the Parliament (and we in obedience unto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112749:14"/>Them) are friends unto the Soule of our dread Soveraigne, in not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, aiding and aſſiſting of Him, to make unnaturall, unlawfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Warres, upon his Parliament and people, which can never be defended, or juſtified, before or unto God, to whom the Mightieſt, as well as the meaneſt, muſt give a ſtrict account of all their actions at the laſt day. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſtand for the Kings Perſon, who obey, joyne and ſide with the Parliament. His Majeſties Perſon is now environed by thoſe, who carry Him, (as far as the eye of humane probability can ſee) upon his own ruine, and the deſtruction of all his good people: which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſeeing, they labour to free him from ſuch falſe hands, by this twoſold meanes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By perſwading, beſeeching and moſt humbly ſoliciting his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to forſake them, and to rejoyce and make glad the hearts of his Parliament and People, by conjoyning himſelfe with Them. But this requeſt, ſuit and ſupplication will not yet be granted, though with much importunity and many loyall expreſſions deſired. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. By labouring to take his evill Councellors from Him, they being confidently aſſured, and piouſly perſwaded of the Kings ſweet diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and readineſſe to comply with them, in any thing which might conduce to the good, either of Church or Common-wealth, if he were not overſwayed and deluded by the fained flattering and crafty coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of thoſe about Him, who look with a ſiniſter eye upon our State. Now this ſeemes to me to be all that is aimed at, in this preſent Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and Martiall deſigne: for the Parliament doe not purpoſely, and in their firſt intentions, intend by their Souldiers to cut off any (for if any be ſlaine by them, it is by accident) but to preſerve and keep the peace of the Kingdome, to maintaine the priviledges of Parliament, the Lawes of the Land, the free courſe of Juſtice, the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the Kings authority and Perſon in his royall dignity, and to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach, arreſt and bring ſuch as are accuſed, or imagined, to be the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and firebrands of the Kingdome, unto a faire, juſt, equall and legall triall, which no man can think <hi>unlawfull</hi> in our <hi>Law-makers.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both <hi>Senatours</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> in the proſecution of this <hi>Deſigne,</hi> ſtand for the ſafety of their Princes Perſon. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſtand for his <hi>State, Wealth, Honour</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi> for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne all theſe together. Kings acquire and accumilate more honour, reſpect, wealth and power, by their meekneſſe towards, tender love of, and vigilant care for their Subjects, and their ſafety (as we ſee in Qu: <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Tiberius,</hi> ſo long as he was ſuch) then by tyrannizing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112749:14"/>over, and cruelly oppreſſing and handling of them, as we ſee in <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula.</hi> If our gracious Soveraigne, would be but pleaſed, to conſider the honour and proſperity which his predeceſſors have enjoyed, by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Advice of their Parliaments, and the diſhonour our Nation hath in divers deſignes received abroad, and the grievous troubles, vexation and diſcord we have had at home, ſince Parliaments have bene diſuſed, and laid aſleepe, he would then certainely ſee, that they ſeeke his wealth, honour, reputation and welfare, who deſire to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile and conjoyne him unto his Parliament, and adviſe him to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne his people by Parliaments, and endeavour to free him from the power, and hands of thoſe, who being themſelves, deſire likewiſe to make him, an enemy unto Parliaments. And</p>
            <p n="4">4. They ſtand for his <hi>Poſterity:</hi> For as evill gotten goods ſlip and waſt away, and ſeldome continue to the third generation: ſo Kings cannot be ſure that their Poſterity ſhall peaceably and ſucceſſively en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their Crowns, except themſelves rule and governe according to Law, righteouſneſſe only eſtabliſhing the Crown and Throne, both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Princes and their Poſterity. And therfore they who aſſiſt not the King, in thoſe things, wayes and courſes, which are illegall, grievous, yea deſtructive to the Common-wealth, are His Childrens and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities beſt Friends.</p>
            <p>I conclude this Queſtion, with this Argument,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
               </label> Thoſe who labour with their lives and eſtates, to defend and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Kings Soule, Honour, Reputation, Wealth, Perſon and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, obey and ſtand for Him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> But the Parliament, and all thoſe who ſide with them in this preſent deſigne, labour with their lives and eſtates, to maintaine and defend the Kings Soule, Honour, Reputation, Wealth, Perſon and Poſterity.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Parliament, and all thoſe who ſide with them in this preſent deſigne, in ſo doing, obey and ſtand for Him.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeeme by what hath bene ſpoken, That neither <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> nor <hi>People,</hi> doth intend the leaſt indignity, diſhonour or diſloyalty to the King: and it is moſt perſpicuouſly and clearely to be ſeene, in all the Kings gracious Meſſages and Declarations, That he hath no deſigne upon his people or Parliament, neither intends any harme, oppoſition or oppreſſion unto them, but profeſſeth to rule them according to Law and equity: How then comes it to paſſe, that either the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not or dare not confide in the King?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> Firſt, it is becauſe they ſee that ſome about the King, are potent with Him, who affect not the Parliament, nor their proceedings, have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112749:15"/>that influence in his counſels, and are ſo predominant and prevalent with Him, that they have often varied and altered him, from his words and promiſes. It is a Maxime in Law; <hi>The King can doe no wrong;</hi> for if any evill act be committed in matter of State, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, if in matters of Juſtice, his Judges muſt anſwer for it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not lay any fault upon the King, but rather impute the faults which have bene of late obvious to many, unto ſome about him, or in great favour with him. Great diſcouragements (I grant) the <hi>Parliament</hi> in their proceedings have had from the <hi>King,</hi> but I dare not imagine that they came originally and primarily from <hi>Him,</hi> but from ſome about him, in regard of that vaſt difference, which is between his words ſpoken to his Parliament, with his own mouth, when he was with them, and the Meſſages ſent unto, and the heavy char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges laid upon them, in his Letters and Declarations, now when he is abſent from Them. He ſaid once, <hi>That in the word of a King, and as He was a Gentleman, he would redreſſe the grievances of his people, as well out of the Parliament, as in it.</hi> Againe, <hi>That he was reſolved to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe freely and clearely upon the Love and affection of his Engliſh Subjects.</hi> Againe, <hi>we doe engage unto you ſolemnly the word of a King, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of all, and every one of You from violence, is, and ever ſhall be as much our care, as the preſervation of us and our children:</hi> And yet what actions and paſſages have of late fallen out, quite contrary to all theſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? the Parliament and all who ſide with it, aſſiſt it, or obey it, in any of the Commiſſions or Orders thereof, being aſſaulted, oppoſed, yea now at laſt proclaimed Traitors. Againe, his Majeſty doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the deteſtation of a Civill War, and abhorres (as he ſaith) the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apprehenſion of it. But this mind neither ſeemed to be in them, who came with his Majeſty to the Houſe of Commons, nor who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him to <hi>Hampton</hi>-Court, and appeared in a warlike man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> nor in diverſe of thoſe who have bene with him and employed by him at <hi>Yorke, Hull, Leiceſter-ſheire, Lancaſhiere, Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet-ſheire, Northampton-ſheire,</hi> and other places. And therefore we muſt needs conceive, that the King is put upon theſe courſes and wayes by his evill Counſellors, and conſequently, that the Parliament cannot confide in his words and promiſes, untill thoſe Councellors be put from him, or forſaken by him. And</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe of that truſt which is repoſed in them. I dare boldly ſay, That if the King ſhould take, or make thoſe Proteſtations, which he makes in his Meſſages and Declarations, unto any one of the Parliament-Houſe, for the performance of any promiſe either unto
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112749:15"/>them or theirs, which did ſimply and ſoly concerne themſelves, they would beleeve and obey him, and without any further queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in him, but they cannot doe this in the caſe, and place, wherein they are. The truſt repoſed by the people in the Parliament, is as well to preſerve the Kingdome by making of new Lawes, when and where there ſhall be need, as by obſerving and putting the Lawes already made, in execution: And therefore in regard of this truſt, they dare not hazard the ſafety, preſervation, and ſole managing of the Land to his Majeſty alone, upon his bare word; becauſe if after ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiding of theirs in the King, upon his faithfull promiſe unto them, he ſhould be over-ſwayed, and ſeduced by ſome wicked Counſellours, to lay ſome illegall impoſitions, taxations and burdens upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as he did ſoone after the granting of the Petition of Right unto the Subject) the Kingdome then would (and might juſtly) blame them as the Authours of their grievances, that had ſo lightly given away their liberties and freedome, by ſubjecting them to an arbitrary power. And indeed, if we will but conſider it without paſſion and partiality, the caſe is no other but this, if the Parliament ſhould who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confide in the Kings words and Promiſes, then there were no more requiſite in them, then this, to make a Declaration unto his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the grievances, burdens, annoyances and illegall proceedings in all, or ſuch and ſuch Courts or Perſons, to the great oppreſſion and heart-breake of the Subject, and having ſo done, to obtaine ſome ſerious Promiſe and Proteſtation, from the King to take-off all theſe preſſures, and to be carefull for the future, that no ſuch ſhall be impoſed upon them, and then to confide in the King, and to breake-up the Parliament, and repaire every one to his own houſe. Now if Senſe, Reaſon, Experience and Knowledge will tell us that this is farre from, or comes farre ſhort of the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and duty of a Parliament, then let us thinke that it is reaſon (as the caſe now ſtands) that the Parliament ſhould not confide in the King. And</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe it were very dangerous for the time to come. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our preſent Soveraigne were as prudent as <hi>Salomon,</hi> yea as pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as <hi>David</hi> (yea like him, a man after Gods own heart) yet it were dangerous for the Parliament ſo to confide in him, that they ſhould truſt the managing of all the great and weighty affairs of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wholy and ſolely unto him, and conſequently granting him an arbitrary power, to rule us, according to the dictates of his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or as the Lord ſhould move and perſwade his heart. This (I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112749:16"/>ſay) is not ſafe, becauſe if they grant, give or ſettle this Power upon him, as King of <hi>England,</hi> then all other ſucceeding Kings will challenge and claime it as due; (or thinke they are not reſpected as their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours) whence if any of them prove Tyrants or tyrannous oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, we ſhall be moſt miſerable and wretched ſlaves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Some perhaps may here object, that although Princes ſhould not uſe their abſolute power by doing alwayes what they liſt, yet they ought not to be circumſcribed, limited, or reſtrained in their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by any tie or obligation of Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. Firſt, it is much better (conſidering the corruption of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) to be with-held by ſome reſtraints of Law and covenant, from that which is evill, and which we cannot juſtifie before God in the Court of Conſcience, then to be boundleſſe, lawleſſe and left to live as we liſt, and to do whatſoever ſeems good in our own eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 2. Secondly, this alſo is better for others: for as the Crane had better to keepe his head out of the Wolves mouth, then to put it into his mouth, and then ſtand at his mercy, whither he will bite off his neck or not, ſo it is better for every wiſe man, rather to keepe and preſerve thoſe immunities, freedomes, prerogatives, and priviledges, which God, and nature hath given unto him, for the preſervation, proſperity and peace of his poſterity, perſon and eſtate, then to diſenfranchize himſelfe and to relinquiſh and reſigne all into the hands of another, and to give him power either to impoveriſh or enrich, either to kill him, or keepe him alive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 7. I come now unto the laſt Queſtion, which is this; ſuppoſe things come unto this height and iſſue, that the King will have the Parliament to confide in him for all they deſire of him, or otherwiſe he will by warres labour to have his will of them, then whether is it lawfull for them by warre to withſtand him? Briefly, whether is this Martiall and Military deſigne, undertaken by the Parliament, againſt that party which is owned and aided by the King, lawfull or unlawfull, and conſequently whither may, and ought we to aſſiſt them or not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. Firſt in generall, I anſwer concerning meanes, by theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; to wit,
<list>
                  <item>1. Meanes muſt be uſed for preventing, and removing of all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall evils.</item>
                  <item>2. The meanes to be uſed for the removall of temporall maladies muſt be alwayes lawfull: for we muſt never doe evill that good may come therof.</item>
                  <item>3. The meanes to be uſed muſt be alwayes conformable, anſwerable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112749:16"/>and ſutable to the malady; as for example, a man muſt not take a ſword to quench a ſire, nor thinke to defend himſelfe againſt an armed foe, (who comes with his Sword drawn, or musket charged, or piſtoll coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to take away his precious life) with faire words; but muſt conſider what remedy, or meanes is moſt proper for the preventing of the evill feared. Now there is no meanes better againſt <hi>offenſive warres</hi> then <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 2. Secondly, I anſwer in generall again, concerning <hi>Actions,</hi> by two Propoſitions, to wit,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which is not lawfull for a private perſon to doe, is lawfull for a publicke; as for example, it is not lawfull for a private perſon to take away the life of one, whom he knowes to have robbed, or murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome one or other, but it is lawfull for the Judge upon the Bench, upon good proof, to do it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which is not lawfull for a private perſon in his own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular cauſe, is lawfull for him in a publick: as for example, had <hi>Faux</hi> bin ready to have given fire to his train, when the <hi>Parliament</hi> had bin full, and in the very inſtant had fallen by a private mans Sword, that act had not bin puniſhable, but praiſe-worthy; but it is not lawfull for a private man to take away the life of one, becauſe he ſees, or knowes that he intends ſome miſchiefe againſt his neighbour or acquaintance; but is bound only to indeavour to hinder, and prevent it, or, at leaſt not to fall upon him, except he can by no other meanes prevent the death and preſerve the life of his brother; and neither is this (I think) lawfull in all caſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That which is not lawfull for a private and particular man to do upon his owne head, is lawfull for him to do being commanded by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; as for example, if it be not lawfull for Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> to ſhut the gates of <hi>Hull</hi> againſt the King, of his owne accord, yet it is lawfull being warranted, and commanded by the Parliament. If it be not lawfull for the Earls of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Bedford,</hi> to take up arms to ſuppreſſe that party which oppreſſeth the Kingdome, of themſelves, yet it is lawfull, by the Order and Commiſſion of Parliament; as is proved by the ſoveraigne Antidote to appeaſe our civill warres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 3. Thirdly, if his Majeſty paſſed an <hi>Act,</hi> not onely of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> but of <hi>Justification,</hi> to our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for their <hi>Warres,</hi> or for taking up weapons againſt his inſtruments; then I cannot ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or how our defenſive Armes ſhould ſo much differ from theirs, that they in ſo doing ſhould be loyall Subjects, and we diſloyall Traitours.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:112749:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> Fourthly,<hi>a Neceſſary War</hi> muſt needs be <hi>lawfull;</hi> for the power and force of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> is ſuch, that it juſtifieth actions otherwiſe unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable. The tranſcendent <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of all politicks, or the <hi>Law Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,</hi> which gives Law to all humane Laws whatſoever, is <hi>Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> The ſafety of the people: and this <hi>Supreame Law of Nations, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus populi,</hi> hath it's immediate rize from the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which teacheth every worme, much more a man, and moſt of all a whole Nation, to provide for its ſafety in time of neceſſity. It is not alwayes lawfull for us to kill thoſe who ſtand at our doores, or who would keep us from comming out of our doores: but if our houſes be blocked up, and we ſo hindred from commerce with others, or from ſeeking reliefe for the ſuſtentation of our own lives, that we and ours are in danger to famiſh, it is lawfull then to iſſue forth with the forces we can make, to fight our ſelves free: how much more lawfull then is it to ſight for the liberty and preſervation of a Church and State? It ſeemes evident by the cleareſt beames of humane reaſon, and the ſtrongeſt inclinations of nature, That every private perſon may defend himſelfe, if unjuſtly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, yea even againſt a Magiſtrate, or his own Father, when he hath no way to eſcape by flight: much more lawfull then is it for a whole Nation to defend themſelves againſt ſuch Aſſaſſinates, as labour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, though the King will not allow them defence. Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the miſeries, and heavy burthens which we muſt lye under, if we undertake not this defenſive Way, and that will ſhew us <hi>the Neceſſity thereof.</hi> Now the evills which we are in danger of, are of that nature, that if they ſhould fall upon us (which the Lord in mercy forbid) we would thinke, that it were better for us to have no being, then ſuch a miſerable being. The preſent Caſe ſeemes to many, who ſee throwly into things, to be threefold. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether Popery or Proteſtaniſme?</hi> and this doubt ariſes from the Kings Aſſiſtants and Agents, in his deſignes, or ſome who are in neere truſt, and of great power with his Majeſty, who (for the moſt part) are either of no Religion, or of any Religion, or of the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or popiſhly inclined and effected. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether ſlavery or liberty?</hi> and this doubt ariſes from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, counſels and perſwaſions of thoſe about the King, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Him that it is lawfull for him to doe what he liſt. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether eſtates or none?</hi> and this doubt ariſes from ſome ſpeeches fallen from ſome in place and authority; that all we have is the Kings; that when there is neceſſity he may command of, or take from us, what he pleaſe; and that he alone is the ſole Judge of this neceſſity.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112749:17"/>The Caſe being thus with us, it ſeemes unnaturall, that any Nation ſhould be bound to contribute its own inherent puiſſance meerely to abet tyranny, and ſupport ſlavery: that is, to fight themſelves ſlaves, or, to affoord aide, aſſiſtance and ſuccour, either with perſons or purſes to thoſe who deſire and endeavour to introduce popery and hereſie into their Church, and to bring themſelves into ſuch ſlavery and bondage, that they may tyrannize over them at pleaſure. And thus the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this <hi>Warre</hi> ſhewes the <hi>lawfullneſſe</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, <hi>Defenſive Warres</hi> are alwayes held <hi>lawfull.</hi>Now the nature and quality of our Warre is <hi>defenſive,</hi> and ſo the more juſtifiable. For
<list>
                  <item>1. The Kings Majeſty miſlead by Malignants, and malevolent Perſons made preparations for Warre, before any ſuch thing was thought upon by the Parliament. And</item>
                  <item>2. We intend not the hurt of others, but our own peace and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; the deſigne being but to ſuppreſſe riots, to keep the peace, and to bring Delinquents to a faire, juſt and legall tryall. And</item>
                  <item>3. Our Armes will be laid down, as ſoone as we are aſſured of a firme peace, and to be ruled as becommeth a free people, who are not borne ſlaves.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, we may gueſſe at the nature of this <hi>Defenſive Warre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers particulars; as namely,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the <hi>Perſons</hi> againſt whom this <hi>Deſigne</hi> is undertaken, which is not the King (as was proved before, and ſhall be further enlarged by and by) but the Malignants of the Kingdome, which we labour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and to bring to puniſhment in a legall way. We goe againſt the Troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the fire-brands of Hell, the <hi>Korahs, Balaams, Doegs, Rabſhakaes, Hamans, Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> of our time. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the <hi>Perſons moſt favouring,</hi> and furthering of this <hi>Defon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive warre,</hi> who are in every place, thoſe who ſtand moſt cordially affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the good of the Common-wealth, and moſt ſincerely addicted to the purity of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the intire profeſſion and practiſe of Religion. And</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the mercy and favour of God towards the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the principall <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Authors</hi> of this <hi>Deſigne.</hi> If we conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. How the Lord preſerved their perſons, from the malicious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Cavaliers, when they went to the very doore of the Houſe. And,</item>
                  <item>2. How He diſcovered the plots and practiſes which were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the bringing up of the Army out of the North againſt Them. And</item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:112749:18"/>
                  <item>3. How He directed them in their ſetling of <hi>Hull,</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> and <hi>Navy,</hi> when things were almoſt come to their height. And</item>
                  <item>4. How he hath from time to time, and ſtill doth encourage them with, or by the <hi>Love, Loyalty, Fidelity, Faith</hi> and <hi>firme Reſolutions</hi> of the moſt part of all Counties, to ſtand and fall, live and dye with them. And</item>
                  <item>5. How hitherto <hi>He</hi> hath extraordinarily turned all the plots of their enemies againſt themſelves, and produced effects quite contrary to thoſe they intended, and fruſtrated all their hopes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If (I ſay) we conſider theſe things, we cannot but ſay of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe,</hi> and <hi>Parliament-men, Surely God is in this place, and in the midſt of you, and preſent with you, and preſident amongſt you;</hi> and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently hope, that the Lord will preſerve and keep you, and finiſh the work he hath begun by you, to your comfort, His glory and our good. And</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we may gueſſe at the goodneſſe of the <hi>Deſigne,</hi> by the <hi>time,</hi> when it was undertaken; for it was not begun untill all other <hi>Meanes</hi> failed; and therfore may be called, <hi>ultimum &amp; unicum remedium,</hi> the laſt and only meanes left. The old Rule was obſerved by them, <hi>Non recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum eſt ad extraordinaria, inijs quae fieri poſſunt por ordinaria,</hi> they tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all fair and ordinary means, and never had recourſe to extraordinary and extreame courſes, untill no other would prevail. We and They have again and again petitioned the King, but cannot prevail; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other politique means failing us, we ought generally (ſeeing the miſery which is threatned is generall) to joyn heads, hearts, hands and eſtates together to ſight for our King, Country, Parliament, ſelves, Religion, Laws, Liberties, lives and all that is ours, becauſe now all is at ſtake. And</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we may cleerly ſee the <hi>lawfullneſſe</hi> of this <hi>Defenſive warre,</hi> if we but look upon the Cauſes and Ends therof, which are many, as namely,
<list>
                  <item>1. The glory of God.</item>
                  <item>2. The good of the Church.</item>
                  <item>3. The propagation of the Goſpell.</item>
                  <item>4. The peace of the Kingdome.</item>
                  <item>5. The proſperity of the Common-wealth.</item>
                  <item>6. The maintenance of the Kings honour, authority, and perſon, in his Royall dignity.</item>
                  <item>7. The liberties and immunities of the Commons.</item>
                  <item>8. The preſervation of the repreſentative Body of the Realme.</item>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112749:18"/>
                  <item>9. The Priviledges of Parliament.</item>
                  <item>10. The Lawes of the Land. And</item>
                  <item>11. The free courſe of Juſtice.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But I will reduce all theſe to foure Heads: to wit, <hi>Gods Glory, the Kings honour, the Parliaments ſafety, and the Kingdomes preſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>Defenſive warre</hi> is undertaken by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for <hi>Gods Glory,</hi> and the maintenance of true Religion. Now we may, yea ought to fight, to maintaine the purity and ſubſtance of Religion, that it may neither be changed into the Ceremonious formalities of Popery nor our conſciences brought into the ſubjection of Romiſh and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This <hi>Defenſive warre</hi> is undertaken by the Parliament for the <hi>Kings honour</hi> and <hi>ſafety.</hi> Now we are bound by the duty of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to defend and maintaine the Kings perſon, honour and eſtate: and therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is our duty to labour by all lawfull meanes to free his <hi>Perſon</hi> from thoſe <hi>Aſſaſſinates,</hi> who violently (by their wicked councell, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and perſwaſion) carry him upon his owne danger and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his liege and moſt loyall Subjects. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is our duty to labour to maintaine the <hi>Kings honour;</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he is over-ruled by thoſe, who (through their ſubtilty) work ſo upon his mild and pliant temper, that they make him appeare to his <hi>Subiects,</hi> yea <hi>forraigne Nations</hi> to be a <hi>Defender of Delinquents</hi> and <hi>evill Counſellours,</hi> againſt his <hi>loving Subiects</hi> and <hi>loyall Parliament,</hi> which tends infinitely to his <hi>diſhonour:</hi> it is then our duty to labour to unwinde and diſentangle him from their practiſes, or by force plucke away their Perſons from about Him. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is our duty to maintain his <hi>Maieſties eſtate.</hi> Now as the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> would often ſay to Q. <hi>Elizabeth, Madam, get but your Subiects hearts, and you need not feare their purſes;</hi> ſo I may ſay, that the love and affection of the Kings Subjects (which his Parliament labours to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich him withall, and to poſſeſſe him of) will be more advantagious unto him for matter of eſtate, then all the Prerogatives and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which his obſcure Counſellours perſwade and indeavour ſo much for, againſt the will and welfare of his people. And if we compare our Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (who would have nothing, but by and from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the love and affection of her people) with the king of <hi>Spain,</hi> who by an arbitrary power tyrannizeth over his Subjects, we ſhall then ſee, as cleare as the Sun, that where Princes by joyning with Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, labour to unite, the hearts, and affections of their people unto
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112749:19"/>them, there riches abound more, both with Prince and people, than in thoſe Kingdomes where all cruell courſes are taken by the King, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh the Commons.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this <hi>Defenſive warre</hi> is under-taken by us, at the Parliaments command, for <hi>their ſafety.</hi> Now both Reaſon and Religion will teach us, that if our <hi>pious Parliament</hi> and <hi>ſage Senate,</hi> for the maintaining of our lives, liberties and lawes, and in, or for oppoſing of it ſelfe (not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings <hi>Perſon, honour</hi> or <hi>eſtate,</hi> but) againſt <hi>his affections miſlead by evill Counſellours,</hi> ſhall be expoſed to danger, diſſolution or death: then it is our duty by <hi>defenſive Warre,</hi> to withſtand that power, or force which is levied againſt <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, this <hi>Military Deſigne</hi> is undertaken for the <hi>Kingdoms pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi> Now both the Laws of God and man (as is againſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction proved in the Treatiſe, called, <hi>A Soveraigne Antidote to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and appeaſe our civill warres</hi>) will beare us out, for taking up <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Armes</hi> for the ſafety of out <hi>Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> That is, if we ſee indeavours and deſignes a-foot, for the reducing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Kingdom, to the condition of thoſe Countries, which are not governed by <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhed Laws,</hi> but by the <hi>will</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> and his <hi>Favourites;</hi> then it is lawfull for us to aſſiſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative body of the Land (whom we entruſt with our laws and liberties) againſt thoſe who reſiſt and oppoſe them, that they may the more eaſily prevaile againſt, and make good their deſignes upon us.</p>
            <p>And therfore although we will never ceaſe to ſue unto the <hi>King,</hi> and humbly to <hi>ſupplicate</hi> the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> yet if we cannot obtain it, without the diſhonour of God, the loſſe of our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Priviledges, Liberties and Laws,</hi> the endangering, yea expoſing of our moſt faithfull Parliament, to imminent perill, and the hazard of his Majeſties Perſon, honour and eſtate; we may then with the peace of God, his holy Angels, and of our own conſciences take up Arms for the <hi>Defenſe</hi> of all theſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
